A Guide to the McLean Estates Civic Association Records, 1959-1999
Virginia Room, Fairfax County Public Library
The McLean Estates Civic Association Records, 1959-1999
Fairfax County Public Library
MSS 05-65
1.5 linear feet
The McLean Estates Civic Association Records consists of 1.5 linear feet spanning the years 1959-1999, and consists of correspondence, meeting minutes, bank statements, newspaper clippings, photographs, and notes.
Cain, Leighton Aubrey (1915-2000)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None
Acquisition Information
Collection created and maintained by Leighton A. Cain. Donated by Merrily Pierce on August 4, 2000.
Historical and Biographical Information
In 1959, the residents of Bryohill McLean Estates founded the McLean Estates Civic Association, later renamed the Broyhill McLean Estates Civic Association. It was organized with the purpose of fostering, promoting and protecting the civic and community interests of the residents of the recently completed Broyhill McLean Estates neighborhood, a development of 250 brick homes constructed during 1957-1958.
On July 21, 1959, the McLean Estates Civil Association adopted their constitution and by-laws. The first regular meeting was held on September 1, 1959, at Franklin Sherman School with 56 members in attendance. Their meetings were held at 8:30 p.m. on the first Tuesday of each month at Franklin Sherman School. The organization initially had a membership of close to 200 families. In 1985, Peggy and Lynn McNulty re-established the civic association, which had become inactive in later years. The civic association holds an annual yard sale, neighborhood fall picnic, block parties, caroling, and home tours.
Leighton A. Cain, former president of the McLean Estates Civic Association, maintained the records found in this collection. Leighton Aubrey Cain was born on March 8, 1915, in Durham, North Carolina to Percy N. and Alice V. Cain. The family later moved to Winston-Salem, and Cain graduated from Reynolds High School in 1931. After graduating, Cain worked as a floor sander for a flooring company and later moved to Washington, D.C. working for the War Department. He married Beatrice Sutherland on February 14, 1943, in Washington, D.C. Cain was a long-time resident of Broyhill McLean Estates and treasurer for the McLean Tress Committee for 30 years. He served as President of the McLean Estates Civic Association starting in 1965, and later as the McLean Broyhill Estates Civic Association historian beginning in 1987. Cain also served as treasurer for the McLean Legal Action Fund in the 1970s. He died on June 25, 2000.
Scope and Content
The McLean Estates Civic Association Records consists of 1.5 linear feet spanning the years 1959-1999, and consists of correspondence, meeting minutes, bank statements, newspaper clippings, photographs, and notes. Correspondence from notable local politicians include A. Claiborne Leigh, Joel T. Broyhill, Stewart Udall, Harry F. Byrd, and Clive DuVall. Also contained is a file on the McLean Legal Action Fund. Subjects include the activities of the McLean Estates Civic Association, development of McLean, Virginia, and the fight against the development of Evans Farm Inn.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
This collection was removed from the McLean Citizens Association Collection, MSS 05-16
Index Terms
Broyhill McLean Estates Civic Association (McLean, Va.); Cain, Leighton Aubrey (1915-2000); Evans Farm Inn (McLean, Va.); McLean (Va.) - History; McLean Legal Action Fund
Container List
- Meeting Minutes, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Meeting Minutes, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Meeting Minutes, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1959-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Questionnaire re: Fences along Route 123, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Christmas Party, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- McLean Broyhill Estates Neighborhood Watch, 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Evans Farm Rezoning, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Treasurer's Reports, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Treasurer's Reports, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Treasurer's Reports, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Bank Statements, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Bank Statements, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Bank Statements, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Bank Statements, 1974-1987 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Membership Dues, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- McLean Bypass Right-of-Way [contains photos], 1961 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Zoning Issues, 1962-1984 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- McLean Legal Assistance Fund, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 20)